Hello, everyone.
In this section, we are going to learn
the types of organizational structure
and spatial features.
Let's first look at how many
types of organizational structures there
are.
According to the practice of most
organizations,
we find that
there are usually
five types of organizational structures.
They are: functional organizational
structure
product organizational structure,
geographic organizational structure,
customer organizational structure and
matrix organizational structure.
The last one is the combination of any
two or three of these four.
Let's look at more details about them.
First of all,  the functional
organizational structure.
This type of structure
groups individuals by specific functions
performed.
In companies which use it,
each department has different functions,
and all similar functions of the company
are grouped in one department.
For example, an industrial corporation
can be divided into
manufacturing department,
the marketing department, the finance
department
the R&D department
the human resources department, etc.
The division of labour is clear-cut,
each one being charged with specific
responsibilities.
In this figure,
we can see that
in the headquarters of the company,
departments are classfied according to
different functions.
For example function A, function B
Function C,Function D and so on.
So, this is the introduction of the
functional department.
Secondly, product organizational
structure.
Companies that follow this
organizes products by category.
For example, the automobile industry.
In an automobile company,
cars,
trucks, buses
and agricultural machinery can be
produced by different departments.
But such kind of division can lead to
a relatively loose management
in the company.
In such case,
Although there are some managers
in the headquarters responsible for
the whole system of management,
each product group
will have an executive or
some managers.
That is to say, staff is reasonably
arranged.
Product organizational structure
is usually adopted by companies
that produce a wide range of products or
by some
diversified companies
whose products are greatly different.
We can find in the figure that at the
top of the hierarchy,
it is still the headquarters.
And below are
product groups according to product
types.
Thirdly, geographic organizational
structure.
Its name suggests that
departments are divided
according to regions.
That is to say, some departments are
located close to the needed facilities,
while some are
close to customers.
Such companies are divided into
departments
according to regions and
have nothing to do with functional
products.
All activities
in certain regions
are managed by
the company's branch in that area.
So, that is the introduction of
geographic organizational structure.
Below the headquarters,
there are
region A, region B and region C, etc.
all divided by the geographical factors.
How many main operating areas there are,
how many divisions will be set.
So, that's the point I want to stress.
Fourthly, customer organizational
structure.
Certain industries
will organize by customer type.
According to this principle,
Each division serves for
one customer group and
does not need to consider the location
of customers.
This is done in an effort to ensure
specific customer expectations are met
by a customized service approach.
For example, commercial banks.
Most of them
have personal credit,
corporate credit
housing mortgage and trust departments.
These are obviously divided by
customers' different needs.
The last one is matrix organizational
structure.
This structure is a mix of
two or more
organizational structures
we just mentioned.
These four structures
have certain advantages
as well as disadvantages,
so some companies choose to
combine two or more of them,
in an effort to take advantage of their
respective strengths.
For example, some companies
adopt a functional organizational
structure under the geographic
organizational structure
while some use a product organizational
structure structure
under the geographic organizational
structure.
To help you understand, I
will introduce you what sorts of
organizational structures banks would
use.
I will take four largest banks in
mainland China as the example.
With headquarters in Beijing,
they set up provincial branches in each
province and
prefecture branches in each region.
Obviously, branches are divided by
areas.
Inside each bank, however,
they would adopt the customer
organizational structure.
So that is the matrix organizational
structure adopted by banks.
Most corporations in our daily life
adopt that structure.
It is rare to see
companies who only
use one organizational structure.
Then, we are going to
focus on the spatial features of these
organizational structures or
we say the spatial differences of
these organizational structures.
Here we pay greater attention to three
of them,
they are: functional organizational
structure,
product organizational structure and
geographic organizational structure.
In the commonly used textbook "Economic
Geography",
the editor Li Xiaojian
uses Stroh Brewery Company as a case
study.
Thia company was a large beer brewery
located in Detroit,
Michigan, United States.
In the picture, the place where the star
is marked is Detroit.
It is obvious to find that this company
adopted the functional organizational
structure.
In a brewery, for example,
production function requires
production and purchasing.
The whole production function is managed
by one vice president.
Then, the marketing.
Promoting beer is a
a very important job for a beer company.
And all marketing businesses are
managed by marketing department.
So a president is needed
in the marketing department.
Similarly, the human resources
department
also needs a manager to control.
Judging from its spatial distribution,
most of Stroh Brewery 's  departments
were located in the eastern part of the
United States,
so its spatial structure was relatively
concentrated.
The next case
we are going to look at is
about product organizational structure.
I want to show you the example of
Atlas Copco company.
It is a
world-leading corporation
headquartered in stockholm, Sweden.
It has three
major business areas
which are grouped according to product
types.
First, industrial construction
department,
then, vacuum technique department and
finally technique related department
these three departments.
It has many plants.
One thing special about it that
each of its product is produced by many
factories and
these factories are located in many
countries.
Another point is that
the production of each product
is managed by factories in one country.
For example, the industrial construction
technique
is mainly in the charge of departments
in Sweden；
the vacuum technique is in the charge of
departments in Belgium；
the technique department is also
in the charge of factories in Sweden.
In this way,
Atlas Copco guarantees its dominant
position in the international market.
And its spatial structure
is quite dispersed.
Compared with the company who uses
functional organizational structure,
the structure of brewery company we just
mentioned
is much more scattered.
This is because Atlas Copco manufactures
products in many countries,
even including those in both sides of
the Atlantic.
Such a kind of decentralized layout.
Next, let's focus on the spatial
features of
geographic organizational structure.
I want to show you the example of AGA
Corporation.
It also has a lot of business areas and
its products are quite diversified.
In the early days,
its main business was
glass production.
This company is a quite typical one who
adopts
the geographic organizational structure.
To improve your understanding,
let's look at the figure 20,
those big black circles are regional
headquarters.
That is to say, AGA sets up headquarters
in each region
to manage
the production and operation activities
in this area.
One thing interesting about the
European headquarters and
North American headquarters
is that
concerning AGA's four headquarters,
there are three headquarters in
Europe, two of which are
South American headquarters 1
and South American headquarters 2.
Why are the South American headquarters
here?
This is because though the South
American market was relatively large
back to the 1980s，
for AGA yet,
at that time,
the South American market was just
entered,
and putting headquarters in
Europe can be safer.
Why Europe was better?
This was because this can help to
communicate with the European
headquarters (the biggest one ) more
efficiently,
in an effort to promote the development
of the South American market.
So, that's the introduction of the
spatial structure
of AGA Corporation.
We can therefore tell that
AGA's spatial structure is much more
dispersed than the two companies I just
mentioned.
Its headquarters are located on all
continents around the world.
So this is all about the
analysis we did regarding
the relationship between companies'
organizational structures
and spatial features.
Before finishing this course, I have one
question for you to think about.
The case studies we just talked are all
foreign companies
and quite old.
So, I want you to think more about
Chinese firms.
What are the organizational structure
and spatial features of Chinese
companies?
For example, can you
analyze Shanghai Electric or
Shanghai Zhenhua Heavy Industries these
corporations in Shanghai?
What are their organizational structures
and spatial features
look like?
What about corporations in other cities
of China?
For example, Huawei in Dongguan,
Guangzhou.
What are the innovations of
Huawei's organizational structure and
its global spatial features?
That's all for today.
Thank you.