Hello, everyone.
In this section, we are going to learn
the international spatial evolution mode
of enterprises.
Today' s lecture focuses on
two representative models.
The first one is Hakansson's global
expansion model.
So, let's get started.
The first idea we need to understand is
the spatial structure of the
enterprise's expansion.
In this model,
we can see that
Hakansson divided the space of
enterprise's expansion
into several parts.
In Figure 16,
the innermost represents
the first centre of the enterprise.
The circle outside the center
is a national market area,
or the national market.
It is the expanded area from the centre
and
where large enterprises tend to locate.
Or it is the area where big companies
are formed.
To be more specific,
it is the area where an enterprise
can expand from a local one to a
national one.
Looking further, it is the outermost
circle.
This circle means
markets in other countries or districts.
Hakansson divided such market into four
parts.
Each part refers to different foreign
market.
Now, I want you guys to pay attention to
the dotted part.
What does that
foreign market mean?
Well, it refers to the market with low
proximity.
That is to say,
transporting goods from the central
place or the domestic market
to this place can cost relatively a lot.
This is the first possibility.
The second possibility is cultural
differences,
the recognition of the target market is
low, and it's hard to enter.
The third one is tariff barriers
or the trade restrictions
are too high or too much,
which make it harder to enter such
market.
So, that's the features of this market.
Next, let's explore how entreprises
expand in
such place.
Hakansson divided such an expansion
into four stages.
For the momentum of expansion ,
he followed a core concept,
the market access.
The expansion of the market is
the primary driving force for the
spatial expansion of enterprises.
The first stage is the
the time when enterprises are
established.
Companies rely on the local environment
a lot.
New companies are often
located in the place where founders live
or work,
just like what we said, the hometown or
some agglomeration places,
industrial clusters and so on.
Before production and operation,
the location has been decided.
In figure 17,
we can see that
there is a black dot in the innermost
circle.
That is the original location of the
factory.
Early expansion is usually the outcome
of increased production capacity due to
increased demand.
Expansion is often achieved by capital
increase.
When the capital increase is restricted
by the site,
or some other limitations,
the location will be changed.
How?
Relocating or building a branch.
Then, the spatial expansion
might occur.
Looking at the figure, we can see that
enterprises mianly expand in the central
place or
around the original location.
In the second stage,
If the local market
can't grow as fast as what
the enterprises expect for,
the marketing activities will soon be
expanded to the domestic market outside
the region.
So company marketing activities
can soon be launched in other places.
While increased business scale and
differentiation of business objectives
can
make the company transform from one
plant to multiple plants.
The sales channels and
the design of the wholesale network
can also be affected by many factors.
Relevant sales organizations
will choose to locate as much as close
to the
consumers and clients.
So we can see in the second stage,
to sell in the domestic market,
enterprises either to set up sales
offices or
to build factories.
Even if they don’t build factories,
they would at least set up sales
organizations
to build a national sales network.
And the original factory is responsible
for
supplying goods.
The third stage,
as the market expands further and
the company almost dominates the
national market,
the sales volumes rise rapidly.
And the enterprise will expand so fast
that
forming a national big one.
When they have the ability to expand
further,
they would consider
foreign markets.
So we say in Economic Geography,
we regard enterprise's export ability
export volumes
and net exports as a significant
competitive factor
of the enterprise.
Then, how companies expand overseas
market?
Well, Hakansson's explanation can answer
it.
Companies will first seek to promote its
products abroad,
usually in those with good exports.
And then establish some sales agents
or choose some overseas agents.
So the agents in this picture is
represented with
herringbone symbol.
It has the lowest risk.
If companies choose to establish sales
agents
in those countries,
the risk can be higher.
Surely, this is under the condition when
the market is very optimistic.
In other words, sales agents think the
market is very good
and has great potential.
The company would then establish its own
sales department in these countries,
or to purchase a previous agent
and upgrade it into a sales department.
This is the second pattern.
Through this pattern,
enterprises can open the targeted
country's market quickly.
The fourth stage,
the overseas market expands very fast.
If enterprises still produce
domestically,
and supply foreign markets by export,
the transportation volume can be very
huge.
Huge transportation volume can lead to
high transportation cost.
Since the costs go up, the product
prices will be increased too.
And finally, the products may not that
competitive.
By this time, there are two choices for
enterprises.
First, producing in the native market,
Second, export.
If the cost of the first one is
higher than the latter one,
the rational choice for the enterprises
is to
build a factory in the local market.
In such case,
the enterprise is no longer a national
one,
but a multinational company
which builds factories
in multiple countries.
Such a kind of multi-location company.
Looking back at the figure,
in the dotted circle
we just mentioned represents the
market which is hard to enter.
So by this time, as the
company operation improves and
scale expands,
some sales agents can be set up or
some factories can be built here.
That means investing overseas
and building factories over there allow
enterprises
to become a local enterprise.
Then they can supply nearby
and avoid trade barriers.
So that is the basic ideas of
Hakansson's
global expansion model.
Then, another point,
what is the expansion momentum?
Well, two words can summarize it.
that is,
market occupation.
Surely, it is not the
only momentum behind entreprises'
spatial expansion.
I want to remind you that
in some cases,
factors such as ensuring the supply of
raw materials (close to raw materials)
and using cheap labor
can make the entreprise invest in
building the factory or merge with other
factories.
In China,
many enterprises or
foreign investment enterprises
are close to the origin of raw
materials.
So, that's all about Hakansson's model.
So, next, I am going to introduce you
Dicken's global shift.
Dicken is a famous economic geographer
who studies globalization
and a representative of the Manchester
School.
Global shift is one of his classic
theories.
This model was
proposed by Dicken in 1986.
He then developed it further in 1990.
The model aims to
reveal entreprises' international
expansion process.
It demonstrates
the ideal evolution of a manufacturing
company
from production in its home country
to production in multiple countries.
Compared with previous models,
this model adds
the rationalization of the company's
internal adjustment
and considers both
the investment process
and the withdrawal of
investment process.
That is to say, both the global
production network
or we say the reorganization process of
sales network
and the domestic reorganization process
or we say a combination of domestic and
global ones
are included.
So the shift is a global one.
This model is divided into five stages.
Let's look at the first stage.
Suppose a multi-factory company
whose production and sales agencies are
located in country 1.
And we call it the home country.
Enterprises supply overseas markets
through exports.
In the second stage,
enterprises begin overseas expansion.
That is to say,
sales agencies and
and sales departments
begin to be set up.
The third stage,
enterprises begin overseas production.
In the diagram, we
can see that overseas expansion
also follows the order,
from far to near,
such kind of contagious diffusion rule.
What does overseas production mean?
As shown in the diagram,
we can see that the market
can be guaranteed.
Why?
This is because after the sales agents'
market survey
or the sales department's operation,
the market is found to be optimistic
or we say the sold products
can cater for local customers.
In such case, the overseas production
will not be that risky.
The fourth stage,
international production and operation
activities further expand.
In other words,
products are produced
and sold
in more countries.
At the last stage,
some reasonable adjustments are
necessary.
That is to say, it is important to
optimize the international network
for production and management
both at home and abroad.
The right part
represents the production.
According to Hakansson,
within the country, different
manufacturers in different countries
only responsible for part of the
production.
And finally, before launching,
products are assembled over factories
within another country.
If this, in those countries,
the international division of labor
is formed.
The network of supplying products to the
global market
is created.
I guess some of you may ask
why it is like this.
Why parts of the products are produced
in some countries but
assembled in
another country?
Well, there are many considerations.
Companies either to make full use of
some places'
production capacity,
or their resources advantage,
or the cheap labor force advantage.
This is the first kind of consideration.
Another consideration is very possible.
That is tax avoidance,
which is considered by many
multinational enterprises around the
world.
Since a multinational enterprise
owns an internal production network,
it can reduce costs by exchanging
internally.
In this way, the loss or
high product prices can be avoided
possibly.
That is to say,
tariff barriers or some tax policies
limitations
in some countries can be avoided.
To be more specific,
that is how Apple Company
does around the world.
Some enterprises in China also follow
this rule.
So, before finishing this lecture,
I have a question for you to think
about.
Since we have studied the four spatial
expansion models,
try to find out the similarities and
differences of them.
That's all
for today.
Thank you.