Hello, everyone.
Previously, we have learned
some basic laws of enterprise spatial expansion.
Following these laws,
when enterprises  expand,
what their specific modes are?
Regarding this issue,
economic geographers conducted a series of studies and
summarized two kinds of patterns.
One is the domestic spatial evolution mode of enterprises;
the other is
international spatial evolution mode of enterprises.
So, first, let's discuss the
domestic spatial evolution mode of enterprises.
In this section,
I am going to introduce you two representative models of it.
The first one is Watts' market area expansion model.
It was proposed by Watts in 1980,
which is based on research on the British brewing industry.
It explains the expansion processes
of many small companies
due to merger.
He assumed that in the studied area,
cities and towns are evenly distributed.
And each town has one company.
The company has only one production facility
or one factory.
These factories produce the same products.
That indicates the homogeneity of the product and
there is no difference in product quality.
Factories sell products in their own market areas.
That is to say, selling goods nearby.
But due to
the different scale of urban population,
people in
different cities and towns
vary greatly.
So, here comes to the next issue.
Enterprises have different market demands
and their production scales are different.
Such difference in production scale
can lead to the differences in production costs.
That means economies of scale are at work.
Larger factories
have relatively low production cost,
so they have an initial competitive advantage
and are more likely to grow faster.
For the expansion model of market area,
to help you understand the assumptions,
I am going to explain the diagram on the screen to you.
On this figure, we can see that
market area expansion model
is separated into t1 t2 t3 t4
four stages.
For the first stage,
stage t1,
we see that there are 25 companies in the researched area.
I want you to pay attention to the 25 companies,
which is the number in this picture.
From pictures t1 to t4,
we can notice that there is a black dot in the lower left corner of each one.
The big black dots have nothing to do
with the number of companies,
but the size of them.
In stage t1,
there are 25 companies.
What I want to remind you is that 1 7 3
in the diagram
don't mean 1 company,
3 companies or 7 companies,
but the size of them.
What else can them refer to ?
Well, they also refer to
the population size of towns served by
enterprises.
So, this is the first point I want you
to pay attention.
After a period of development,
in stage t4,
we can see that only 3 companies left.
In this stage,
the dot in the bottom left corner is 60.
What does 60 mean?
Well, it indicates the size of this
company.
In other words, this company
merged with some other companies，
and 60 refers to
the scale after merging.
So, that's explanation of 60.
And other numbers represent the same
thing.
The only difference is that there are
only 3 companies left in stage t4.
In the diagram,
the black dot here represents companies.
I guess you may wonder
why there are 4 black dots.
This is because in the t4 stage,
the black dot at the top left
is a branch factory
or a sub-factory
of the company whose size is 60.
This place has a large market,
so factories tend to be
located here.
But these two belong to one single
company.
Such kind of meaning.
Correspondingly,
the market area of ​​those companies
who have survived and expanded has also
been expanded,
covering the market area of ​​many small
companies
And it ’s the hexagon we talked about in
previous lectures.
So, finally,
after four stages' mergers,
such kind of market area is formed.
Next, we are going to focus on
the applicability of this model.
It illustrates that companies with
initial cost advantages
continuously expand outward in the
market area by
merging many neighboring small
businesses.
It is true in most cases.
But there are some uncertainties we need
to pay attention.
The first is that
it is developed on the assumption of
economies of scale.
Or we say economies of scale here is the
momentum
or the driving force.
But, in some sectors where economies of
scale are not prominent,
it may not that applicable .
While, in the beverage industry
or the brewing industry we just
mentioned,
its economies of scale in production are
outstanding,
its sales are targeting at the public
and the quality of the products
is not much different,
so this industry's sales volume is
closely related to its scale
and the sales volume is closely related
to the price.
That is to say, consumers demand of this
industry have
price sensitivity,
or the price elasticity,
which further strengthens the economies
of scale.
For companies that
produce some parts of the products,
their spatial expansion
may not like this.
Another point you need to focus on is
that
it is assumed that
the market area expands in an ideal way.
But in reality,
there may be a discontinuous market
expansion
due to some conditions.
Or we say the market area expansion
we talk about here
is a very typical contagious diffusion.
In fact, this model does not consider
the hierarchy diffusion
or channel diffusion
or transportation and diffusion
these forms of diffusion.
Next, the second model we are going to
introduce in
the domestic spatial evolution mode of
enterprises is
Taylor's enterprises metamorphosis model
and
the spatial evolution model.
This model was
proposed by Taylor in 1975.
It also aims to
explain a company's spatial expansion
process within a country.
But different from Watts',
his regional evolution model
was based on the British ironmaking
industry.
If we say Watts focused on light
industry,
Taylor's research object
was a heavy industry.
Taylor also analyzed the mechanism of
the evolution process in detail.
Now, let's look at
some key concepts in
Taylor's enterprises metamorphosis model
and
regional evolution model.
He distinguished four spatial scales.
The first one is the local, the smallest
scale.
the second one, the regional,
the third one, the national,
the fourth one,  the multinational.
So,  there are four spatial scales.
Next point, three thresholds.
What three thresholds?
The company has to
cross three thresholds
when expanding from the local to the
multinational.
In this figure,
three thresholds are clearly marked
here.
These three thresholds
are closely related to the three spaces
we are going to talk about.
Each time a threshold is crossed,
a metamorphosis of the enterprise is
caused.
In crossing the threshold,
the company's activity space
which is also called physical contact
space
is a specific scope of business.
It is the fastest.
Then, the information space.
Finally,  the decision space.
The last space crosses
relatively slow.
So that is the introduction of the
metamorphosis model.
Taylor's model
integrates such a spatial scale
thresholds and metamorphosis.
Next, let's look at the
evolution mechanism of enterprise
metamorphosis.
Concerning such mechanism,
we first discuss from the establishment
of the enterprise.
Location is very important for the
establishment of new enterprises.
Many studies show that hometowns
are the places
where the entreprises
tend to locate their factories at the
beginning of businesses.
Why people choose to start a business in
their hometowns?
Mainly because people have grwon here
and
they have some social contact or they
are familiar with such places.
So thinking about it in this way,
we can see that hometown is an activity
space.
People control a lot of
information space over this space.
After the company is established,
the company's activity space,
information space and decision space
are limited to the local.
In the process of the expansion of
the information space and decision space
by the activity space,
we can think about why such kind of
expansion occurs?
At the beginning, for example
the business is relatively small,
once the company satisfys the local
market,
and operates well,
have customers outside the local,
by this time,
the physical activity space can be
expanded.
As the physical activity space expands,
you have to understand the information
outside the local,
the market demand outside of local.
At this time, on such basis, companies
make decisions
to produce, sell and
transport.
So then the physical space
information space and decision space
begin to cross.
While, at this time, the entreprise
metamorphosis
is caused.
So, metamorphosis becomes the
thresholds and obstacles in the
development of business organization.
Here we also need to look at
enterprises' spatial expansion
in the context of risk and uncertainty.
Why we keep emphasizing the improtance
of
information space and decision space?
Because they are related to the issues
of risks.
To be more specific, sales agencies
have the lowest risks and
do not require additional investment.
But setting up a sales department
or building a warehouse in a place
can occupy a lot of space and
the land rent can be high.
Specialized management is also needed.
All of these require much capital
investment.
So it's more risky.
Perhaps you may ask why not just build a
factory over there?
Well, I want to say factory costs much
more.
Land, production lines,
equipment, employees, and production
all need quite a large amount of
investment.
Once the investment fails,
entreprises will be hit hard.
Taylor also developed a
idealized entreprise spatial expansion
model
In this model,
it is assumed that a country is divided
into four regions.
Let's look at the upper right corner of
this picture，
the 3 big black dots in the three
regions
show that there are three big industrial
agglomeration centres.
And three little white circles
refer to three smaller secondary urban
centers.
Under such a regional pattern,
let's see how a local company
expands into a national one?
If entreprises want to cross to other
regions,
they should cross the first threshold.
Then, how?
Well, a sales office can be set up
in the adjacent area.
Or to reduce the risk to the minimal,
a sales agency
or an agent
can be formed here.
Enterprises can also form a sales
office, helping
sells products in another region.
That's the way how to cross the space.
So, to summarize, we can say that
enterprises can
experience metamorphosis by
such kind of way of spatial expansion.
From a regional or local factory, or
an entreprise with only one department
to a multi-functional, multi-location
multi-factory and multi-sector
national one.
Following this principle,
you guys can analyze the spatial
expansion more.
Enterprises can even become a
multinational one.
Surely, operating in different countries
can be more challengeable and more risky
compared with just doing businesses at
home.
That is to say, the thresholds
or information spaces
and decision spaces can be stronger.
So that is the explanation of
Taylor's enterprise metamorphosis and
spatial evolution model.
It is easy for you to understand through
such a diagram.
Before finishing this lecture, I have a
question for you to think about.
Try to compare the similarities and
differences
between the Watts' model and
Taylor's model and
and these models'
practical application.
Can we
find a typical business case in China
to see how it was developed?
So, that's all for
the study of domestic space expansion
model.
This is the end of this section.
Thank you.